<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Infirmity inducing to conformity, or, A scourge for impudent usurpers, and a cordiall for impotent Christians preached not long since in St. Peter's the Poore ... and in St. Pancras Church-yard when it could not be admitted into the church, July 8, 1649 / by Peter Bales ...</title>
            <author>Bales, Peter, 1547-1610?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B549</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13074841</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13074841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30126)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 407:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Infirmity inducing to conformity, or, A scourge for impudent usurpers, and a cordiall for impotent Christians preached not long since in St. Peter's the Poore ... and in St. Pancras Church-yard when it could not be admitted into the church, July 8, 1649 / by Peter Bales ...</title>
                  <author>Bales, Peter, 1547-1610?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97183:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>INFIRMITY Inducing to CONFORMITY: <hi>OR,</hi> A Scourge for impudent Uſurpers; <hi>AND,</hi> A Cordiall for impotent Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Preached not long ſince in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter</hi>'s the <hi>Poore, Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, London;</hi> and in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pancras</hi> Church-yard when it could not be admitted into the Church. <hi>July</hi> 8. 1649.</p>
            <p>BY PETER BALES, Maſter in Arts; and a perſecuted Miniſter of the holy Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 24.15, 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Lay no wait (ô wicked man!) againſt the houſe of the righteous; and ſpoyle not his reſting place:</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ver. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl> For, a juſt man falleth ſeven times and riſeth up againe.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>TERTUL.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Conditio preſentium temporum provocat hanc admonitionem noſtram.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed in the Yeare, M.DC.L.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97183:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97183:2"/>
            <head>To all Royall and Loyall Engliſhmen, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Nos Omnes,</hi> in my <hi>Text,</hi> hath brought me to <hi>Vos omnes</hi> with this chartaceous Preſent; which, in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and ſome confidence of your favourable accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and conſtruction, (having already experimentally found your benevolence and bounty towards me and mine) I doe now tender to your religious conſideration: To you (I ſay) doth this my poore labour properly belong, who are ſo endowed with the grace of <hi>God,</hi> as to go out of your ſelves, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> may enter in; to exina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite your ſelves, that you may partake of the fulneſſe of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> knowing, that all your Perfection (as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith) conſiſts in acknowledging your owne Imperfection. As for <hi>ſelf-applauding Uſurpers,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-juſtifying unjuſt Ones,</hi> who doe <hi>meaſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with themſelves,</hi> neither my <hi>Text,</hi> nor this <hi>treatiſed Sermon</hi> doth appertaine unto them; unleſſe to be as a <hi>whip</hi> to laſh them, I am certaine, not as a <hi>cordiall</hi> to comfort them. There is but one <hi>truth,</hi> yet encountred with as many <hi>falſhoods</hi> as there were gobbets and ſhreds of diſmembred <hi>Pentheus;</hi> and ſurely, never with more, in this <hi>quondam</hi> flouriſhing <hi>Church,</hi> then in theſe our dayes, when and where giddy-headed Phantaſie and ambitious Liberty doe moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſly overſway the Judgment, and overthrow the Law.</p>
            <p>Sirs, I am not <hi>Dominis Arriſor,</hi> neither <hi>Eccleſiae aut Reipublicae Arroſor,</hi> I neither faune upon my <hi>Maſters,</hi> nor devoure the <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> But I beſeech you by the meekneſs and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Chriſt, Doe not dare to make your ſelves of the number, or to compare your ſelves to them which praiſe themſelves; yet they underſtand not that they meaſure themſelves with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and compare themſelves with themſelves, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>10.12.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>in ſe ſcipſos metiuntur,</hi> in themſelves they meaſure themſelves, that is, through a vaine perſwaſion of their owne excellency they arrogate to themſelves more than is meet and right.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97183:3"/>
            <p> The humility of the mind, is the ſublimity of a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and the more vile and baſe we are in our owne eyes, the more glorious are we in <hi>God</hi>'s account.</p>
            <p>God made the Heavens before the Earth: but Man muſt lay his foundation firſt in the Earth (in rightly weighing the ponderouſneſſe of his depraved diſpoſition, and terrene affection) before ever he ſhall come to Heaven. Let humility (therefore) be nouriſhed by you: Firſt, by the aſſiduity of Subjection. Secondly, by the meditation of ſublime matters. Laſtly, by the daily and ſerious conſideration of your owne frailty: So, ſhall you not be many <hi>Maſters,</hi> and then your commendation (not condemnation) will be the greater. For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deare <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> Though we all offend in many things, I have not wittingly and willingly offended (in this diſcourſe) <hi>God</hi> or Good-men in any thing: I am not prodigall of pompous wit, or choice of words, there may be abſurdities and literall faults; if there be, I crave your friendly pardon and pretermiſſion, and for the ſubſtance your courteous acceptance: God grant it may be as profitable unto you as it was intended for you. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your poore Servant, in, and for the Lord Jeſus; <hi>PETER BALES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97183:3"/>
            <head>INFIRMITY Inducing to CONFORMITY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. IAM. 3. part of the 2.</hi> v.</bibl>
                  <p>In many things wee offend all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is a <hi>Text</hi> of holy <hi>Scripture</hi> whereunto all Licentious <hi>Libertines,</hi> Independent <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and Prophane <hi>Atheists</hi> doe (though moſt unjuſtly) lay a peculiar claime, that it might be as a <hi>Covert</hi> to hide, or a <hi>Paraſite</hi> to palliate all their Diabolicall <hi>Stratagems,</hi> Machiavellian <hi>Deſignes,</hi> and moſt Deteſtable <hi>Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations:</hi> viz: <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Be not thou juſt overmuch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is a <hi>place</hi> of holy <hi>Scripture</hi> wherein all <hi>God</hi>'s deare <hi>Children</hi> have a due <hi>intereſt</hi> and a juſt <hi>right</hi> and <hi>title;</hi> which is as a <hi>ſcourge</hi> to correct, or a <hi>two-edged Sword</hi> to confound all their Enemies, and a comfortable <hi>Directory</hi> for themſelves: <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. <hi>In multis offendimus omnes,</hi> (i.e.) <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Petrus Tenorius</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> having a long time conſidered the weighty reaſons on each ſide, whether <hi>Salomon</hi> was damned, or ſaved; in fine (remaining ſtill doubtfull of the truth hereof) cauſed him to be painted in his Chappel half in Heaven, and half in Hell: Whether this Father deſerved, for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97183:4"/>this his uncharitable incredulity, commendation or condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let all good Men judge: Yet, am I confident, that I ſhall not deſerve any blame, if I ſhould pourtray a good Chriſtian half in Heaven and half on Earth; Halfe in Heaven; by reaſon of his regenerate part; devout oriſons, divine contemplation, and heavenly converſation: Half on Earth; in regard of his naturall part; inherent corruption, Sathan's ſuggeſtion, and the world's infection: A Child of God being like unto Saint <hi>Anſelm</hi>'s Bird ſoaring with winged ſwiftneſſe towards Heaven; but being tied (by the Shepherd's wanton Boy) to an heavie ſtone with a long ſtring, was forcibly brought downe to the Earth againe. We are preſt and ready to flie (as it were) to doe the Will of our heavenly Father, when we have taſted the firſt fruits of the Spirit; but immediately are pull'd downe againe to our owne earthly imaginations and ſinfull affections, by the ſtone-weight of our owne depraved nature: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>For, in many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words doe afford us Two generall parts:</p>
            <p n="1">I: The firſt is the <hi>Delictum,</hi> or Offence: Aggravated,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by its perennity or aſſiduity: It is not ſaid, we have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, or ſhall offend; but, we doe offend: like a quotidian Ague, it takes and ſhakes us every day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by its multiplicity: it cannot ſay as <hi>Elijah</hi> did, <hi>I am left alone, and they ſeek my life: Non in pancis, ſed in multis,</hi> not in a few things, but in many things we doe offend.</p>
            <p n="2">II. The ſecond mentioneth the Delinquents or Offenders: Deſcribed,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by a plurall Perſonality and a gracious affinity both in reſpect of God and themſelves. <hi>Nos,</hi> We.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by their Generallity, not partially but univerſally expreſſed, <hi>Omnes,</hi> All. <hi>Et qui dicit omnes excludit neminem,</hi> and in ſaying [all] he excepts or exempts none at all, from offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and that in many things. <hi>In multis offendimus omnes,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Text is as an eye in the head wherewith we may ſee our owne Deformity: Or as a tongue in the head by which we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97183:4"/>may and muſt confeſſe our manifold infirmities and aberrations. It is as a Garden full of ſweet flowers intermixt with many and diverſe ſtinking weeds. It is as a flouriſhing Vine laden with ſowre grapes, which (by God's aſſiſtance) I ſhall preſſe; that with the juyce of them your appetites may be more and more ſharpened to eate and digeſt the true bread of life.</p>
            <p>Begin we therefore with the firſt generall part of my Text, which is, the <hi>Delictum</hi> or <hi>Offence:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vulgar Latine tranſlates the originall word, <hi>Offendimus,</hi> we <hi>offend,</hi> or <hi>ſtumble.</hi> Sinne (indeed) is <hi>offendiculum,</hi> a ſtumbling ſtone, or block of offence; and it lieth in our way, which way ſoever we turne our ſelves; ſo that if we ſtumble not upon it, but miſſe it; it was the grace of God that upheld us, and gave us warning of it, that we might have the more free progreſſe in our journey to the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi> Sin offendeth God, our ſelves, and our Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it offendeth God, who is Holineſſe it ſelfe, and therefore cannot but abominate it in his Creatures. It cauſed him to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that he had made Man, and to be ſory at his very heart, Gen.</hi> 6.6. Yea, ſinne is ſo offenſive to him, that nothing but the merits and interceſſion of his beloved Sonne and our alone Saviour, Jeſus Chriſt, can appeaſe his wrath, and turne away his diſpleaſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it offendeth our ſelves, and that, Firſt, in reſpect of the new man or regenerate part: <hi>If thy right eye offend thee pluck it out, Mat.</hi> 5.29. where by the eye, hand and foot, our Saviour meaneth, the luſts of the fleſh and the concupiſcences of the old man, which doe often moleſt and offend the new man, in its running in the path of God's commandements. Secondly, in reſpect of the Conſcience; every ſinne is a ſickneſſe, and a ſoare: It is <hi>flagellum animae,</hi> yea, <hi>mors animae,</hi> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> calls it, the ſcourge of the ſoule, and death of the ſoule. When the conſcience is throughly awakened for ſinne, it caſteth the ſoule into many pangs and throws, and leaves it void of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, till Chriſt Jeſus brings it into his wine-cellar of conſolation, and ſpreads over it the banner of his love: If he doth not, it proves, not onely an Accuſer, and a Judge; but an Executioner alſo.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97183:5"/>
            <p> Thirdly, it offendeth our Neighbours: it made the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David</hi> complain bitterly in his abode with incorrigible, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable, and prophane Perſons, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. <hi>Woe is me, that I am conſtrained to dwell with Meſeck, and to have my habitation among the tents of Kedar: My ſoule hath long dwelt with thoſe that are Enemies unto peace.</hi> The Sodomits unlawfull deeds vexed <hi>Lot</hi>'s righteous ſoule from day to day, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. And theſe five ſeverall waies, eſpecially doe we offend our Neighbours: 1. By evill example. 2. By evill counſell. 3. By baſe detraction. 4. By falſe doctrine. 5. By the abuſe of Chriſtian liberty. <hi>Let</hi> therefore <hi>our light ſo ſhine before men, that they ſeeing our good works, may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 5.16. <hi>Let us</hi> with Saint <hi>Paul, therein exerciſe our ſelves to have alwaies a conſcience void of offence toward God, and toward Men,</hi> Act. 24.16. <hi>Let us give no offence neither to the Jewes, nor to the Grecians, nor to the Church of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.32. In a word, Let us not doe any thimg with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith and Charity: Whoſoever walketh according to this rule, <hi>Peace ſhall be upon him, and upon the Iſrael of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, we doe not onely give, and take offence our ſelves, ſtumble our ſelves and make others ſtumble; but we alſo fall, and ſo our beſt Tranſlation renders it, <hi>In multis labimur omnes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>we fall many waies.</hi> This Fall is not corporall, but morall; yet by a Corporall we may underſtand a Morall fall; for as he that falleth, in regard of the ſight of his body, commeth lower, and withall, ordinarily taketh a bruiſe, even ſo is it in a morall fall: Our nature by it becomes not onely more baſe and vile, but more feeble alſo: But this phraſe importeth a difference of Sinners: ſome draw iniquity with the cords of vanity; others account it vanity, and doe feele vexation of ſpirit to be drawne into iniquity with cords: Some doe take pleaſure in ſinning; others doe eſteem it a ſinne to take pleaſure therein: ſome doe ſinne through malice; ſome through frailty: ſome comit ſinne; ſome fall: They ſinne through malice, in whom the principles of conſcience are corrupt, who wittingly and willingly commit ſinne with greedineſſe: neither before the fact feeling any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy, nor after the fact conceiving any ſorrow: Theſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>darkneſſe, light; and light, darkneſſe; evill, good; and good, evill;</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaketh, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.20. It is improper to ſay
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97183:5"/>that theſe doe fall into ſinne; for, will any one of ſet purpoſe fall to hurt himſelfe? To be overtaken in a fault, (which phraſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> uſeth to the Galatians, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.) is nothing elſe but this <hi>falling</hi> in my Text. The phraſe reacheth onely thoſe who ſinne, <hi>dum aut latet veritas, aut compellit infirmitas,</hi> as venerable <hi>Bede</hi> ſpeaketh, either when they are ſophiſtically circumvented, or unawares tranſported, and ſo take a fall. <hi>Let him</hi> therefore <hi>that thinks he ſtands to himſelfe take heed leſt he fall,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. For, it is not ſaid, we have fallen, or ſhall fall; (though true e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) but, we doe; noting unto us the aſſiduity, or daily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our falling; which is the firſt Particular of the firſt Generall, and comes now in order to be handled.</p>
            <p>We doe continually ſinne, even from the morning of our youth, to the evening of our old age: yea, from our very cradles, even unto our graves. Our life is a dying, and our dying is our life: Our breathing under Heaven is a breathing againſt Heaven, and we live not a day without ſinne. <hi>A juſt man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prov.</hi> 26.16. <hi>falleth ſeven times,</hi> yea, <hi>(in a day)</hi> every day. This is the common addition, frequent in the antient Fathers, though not found in the Originall. But, God himſelf ſaith, that <hi>the imagination of mans heart is evill from his youth, Gen.</hi> 8.21. And (in <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5.) he ſaith, <hi>The imaginations of the thoughts of his heart are onely evill continually:</hi> The Hebrew renders it, <hi>every day.</hi> Should not this teach us all to be ready to forgive the frequent, continuall, and daily fallings, and offences of our Brethren?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid unto our Saviour, <hi>How often ſhall my Brother ſinne againſt me, and I ſhall forgive him? unto ſeven times? Jeſus ſaid unto him, I ſay not to thee, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto ſeven times! but, unto ſeventy times ſeven times.</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> makes this queſtion upon theſe words, Why (ſaith he) doth our Saviour ſay, Seventy times ſeven times; and not an hundreth times eight times? The anſwer (ſaith he) is ready; From <hi>Adam</hi> to Chriſt were ſeventy Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; therefore, as Chriſt forgave all the tranſgreſſions of whole mankind parted and diffuſed into ſo many Generations; ſo alſo we ſhould remit as many offences, as, in the terme and compaſſe of our life, are committed againſt us.</p>
            <p>Againe, what doth this teach us to act towards our ſelves? Surely, every day to examine our owne hearts in our chambers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97183:6"/>and to be ſtill: To keep by us an Ephemerides of our thoughts, words, and deeds: To practice <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his golden verſe and adviſe, Before (ſaith he) thou ſuffereſt ſleep to poſſeſſe thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eyes, aske thy ſoule thrice over, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Whither have I gone? What have I done? What opportunity have I loſt? Or, to imitate <hi>Sentius,</hi> who, when the day was paſt and the night come wherein he ſhould take his reſt, would aske his mind, What evill haſt thou healed this day? What vice haſt thou ſtood againſt? In what part art thou bettered? And then finding our fallings and offences, let us be inſtant in Prayer and Repentance: We doe continually of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our gracious God, making his diſpleaſure to ariſe; let us therefore continually uſe the meanes which conduce to a Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and that is, Prayer: He that prayeth moſt frequently is the beſt Chriſtian, and hath the moſt intereſt in Heaven, He lives moſt comfortably, and dies moſt cheerfully. And being our whole life is a time of ſinning; let us make our whole life a time of repenting. <hi>Redeat homo, c.</hi> 7. ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> Let a man returne by daily lamentations to that from whence he is fallen by vaine delectations: Let not the Sunne ſet in Gods anger to night us: Let us not live a day longer before we begin to live indeed: Let us not climbe up into our beds, before we have climbed up into God's favour: Let not the eyes of our bodies be ſhut with ſleep, before the eyes of our ſoules be opened by repentance. It would be (doubtleſſe) a great deale of eaſe to our troubled ſpirits, if this our continuall offending were confined to ſome one pettie ſinne, whereunto we are unwillingly carried, by our owne natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall concupiſcence, provoking, by the Devils ſubtilty, perſwading, and by the world's vanity, alluring; But, behold our wretched condition, by reaſon of ſinnes multiplicity; which brings me to the ſecond Particular of the firſt Generall: <hi>viz:</hi> We offend, <hi>in multis,</hi> in many things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mille modis offendimus,</hi> we doe offend a thouſand waies: we run through more ſinnes every day than there be ſignes in the Zodiacke: Our graces are in a Shekel; but our ſins in an Ephah: Our graces are diminutives; but our ſinnes are augmentatives. Sinne like hereſie, is of an encroaching nature; as one hereſie proveth another; ſo doth our ſinne uſher in another, the leſſer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97183:6"/>alwaies making roome for the greater: Let us not therefore onely weigh our ſinnes; but alſo number them: If they ſeem ſmall, we cannot count them; for, as the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12. <hi>Who can underſtand his Errors?</hi> or, <hi>Who can tell how often he offendeth?</hi> A negative interrogation is as much as an affirmative propoſition, and an affirmative interrogation as much as a negative propoſition: Who can tell how oft he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth? that is to ſay, not any one can tell; <hi>viz:</hi> if we conſider the acts of ſinne; but we may and muſt number the kinds of ſinne, and ferret them out as ſo many <hi>Achans,</hi> by the poll. Conſider (my Brethren) that we are guilty of ſinnes of Omiſſion, and Commiſſion; of Ignorance, and Knowledge; of Weakneſſe, and Wilfulneſſe, &amp;c. We ſinne within us, and without us: Within us, by the Faculties of our ſoules, by the words of our mouth, and by the works of our hands.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We ſinne in our Underſtanding, Will, Affections, and Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In our Silence, and in our Speeches, whether Ordinary or Extraordinary, whether Civill or Sacred.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In our Actions, whether Paſſive or Active; and in Active, whether Naturall or Morall; and in Naturall, whether they be ſuch as tend to our Being, or Wel-being: and in Morall, whether Politicall, or Eccleſiaſticall. We ſinne againe, by the outward Members of our bodies, as Feet, Hands, Eyes, and Eares, when we uſe them as members of unrighteouſneſſe. What ſhall I ſay? Doe we not <hi>in many things</hi> offend all? Surely, in our very beſt Actions we doe ſcatter many imperfections, and we faile, either in the end matter, manner, or meaſure of our obedience. Should the Lord call us unto a ſtrict triall, how ignorant would our knowledge be found? How fraile our faith? How wavering our hope? How proud our humility? How froward our pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? How cruell our mercies? How lukewarme our prayers? How ſuperficiall our repentance? Alas! alas! Many are the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of our ſoules, many the deformities of our lives; they are more in number than the haires of our heads, or the ſands on the ſea-ſhore; ſo that we may well ſay with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 130.3. <hi>If thou, ô Lord, be extreame to marke what is done amiſſe, who can be able to ſtand?</hi> Surely, that who, (ſaith Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97183:7"/>no body at all. Let us therefore (with <hi>Martha,</hi> though in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe) be much troubled for theſe many things, wherein we offend all; and (with <hi>Mary</hi>) chuſe the better part, that ſhall never be taken from us, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.41, 42. Yea, let us, who offend in many things, beware that we give not our ſelves the reins to offend in every thing: For, the Saints of God, though they doe offend <hi>in multis,</hi> yet, not <hi>in omnibus,</hi> though in many things, yet, not in all things: Wherefore, all things worke together for the beſt to them; but, <hi>non ex ipſorum meritis; ſed ex merâ ipſius miſericordiâ,</hi> not as flowing from the ſtinking puddle of their owne baſe merit; but, as iſſuing out of the cleer fountaine of God's free and meer mercy: For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> Which brings me to the ſecond Generall part; wherein I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the <hi>Delinquents,</hi> or <hi>Offenders,</hi> deſcribed two waies:</p>
            <p>Firſt, by a plurall perſonallity, and gracious affinity; both in reſpect of God and Themſelves: <hi>Nos,</hi> We.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by their generallity, not partially; but univerſally expreſſed: <hi>Omnes,</hi> All.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Begin we with the firſt, <hi>Nos offendimus,</hi> we offend. Are the KING-Depoſing, KING-Killing, ambitious, Jeſuited Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents; the rigid, uſurping Presbyterians; the love-ſick Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts; the milk-white Browniſts; the lawleſſe Antinomians; the Saint-reigning Millenaries; free-willed Arminians; new-fangled, and ſchiſmatically intangled Reformers (I ſhould have ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers;) meritorious and ſupererrogatory Romaniſts, with many more, the like Offenders, comprehended: Are they (I ſay) comprehended in this <hi>We,</hi> in the Text? Surely, we find them not in the ſacred Pages of holy Writ, much leſſe in this word <hi>We:</hi> But find them we ſhall, in their own fanatick Pamphlets, blurd with ſelf-juſtifying; yet, moſt damnable errours; making the holy Scripture a Noſe of Wax, or a Ship-man's hoſe, any thing, or nothing, to ſerve their owne turnes; like Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>'s Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, of whom he thus ſpeaketh, <hi>Scripturas ad ſuum ſenſum; non ſuum ſenſum ad Scripturas adducunt:</hi> They do not reduce their ſenſes unto the Scripture, when they read; but doe wickedly captivate the Scriptures unto their owne ſenſes and meanings. Let us therefore looke upon the plurall perſonallity, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining not a graceleſſe, but a gratious company, ſuch as are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97183:7"/>
               <hi>magnum genus,</hi> (as <hi>Chryſologus</hi> terms them) of a right <hi>noble ſtock:</hi> Yea, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Of the blood-Royall, in a</hi> ſpirituall ſenſe: For, God is their Father, Chriſt their elder Brother, the Holy Ghoſt their Comforter, the Church their Mother, Heaven their inheritance, and Regeneration their Evidence; yet, are they Offenders in many things, and this they doe in humility and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of heart acknowledge. In many things (ſaith Saint <hi>James) We</hi> doe offend: I, an Apoſtle, and you Profeſſors, even <hi>we;</hi> who are <hi>called, juſtified, ſanctified,</hi> and <hi>redeemed</hi> by the pretious blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> That the deare Children of God, both Miniſters, and People have been, are, and ſhall be Offenders in many things, even to the world's end; not onely my Text, but other places of holy Scripture doe ſufficiently declare. Was not <hi>Noah</hi> a man beloved of the Lord, and a Preacher of righteouſneſſe? yet, was he not inebriated with his owne wine? <hi>Vino captus, qui diluvium fugerat,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> He was freed from a deluge of water, and drowned in a deluge of wine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.21. Had not <hi>Lot</hi> his Epithete of <hi>Juſt, Juſt Lot?</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8. And was not he vexed at the uncleanly converſation of the wicked? And did not he ſee the Sodomites burnt with fire for their luſts? yet, did not he doe wickedly, and (being delivered) burne with inceſt? <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſinned, in ſwearing, <hi>By the life of Phardoh, Gen,</hi> 42.15. <hi>Aaron</hi> ſinned, in making the <hi>golden Calfe</hi> for the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to worſhip, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.21. And <hi>he</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> ſinned, in murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 12.7, 8. The Prophet <hi>Jonah</hi> tranſgreſſed in flying from <hi>Joppe</hi> to <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and in juſtifying his unjuſt anger for the Gourd. <hi>Moſes</hi> (though the Servant of the Lord, and the meekeſt Man upon the earth) offended in unbelief and anger, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.15. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> was a man according to God's owne heart, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. and in the ſtate of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; yet, his heart was uncleane, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. and <hi>he</hi> fell into the ſinne of adultery, hypocriſie, murther, and ambition, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. &amp; 24. <hi>Salomon,</hi> the wiſeſt Man upon the earth, committed folly. <hi>Job</hi> the patienteſt, yet not altogether to be excuſed of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; nor <hi>Elias</hi> of paſſion; nor the Sonnes of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; nor <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> of diſſimulation, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. No, nor the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> her ſelf, of vain-glory. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, yet puſilanimous; Confident, yet Diffident; ſo faithfull
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97183:8"/>that Chriſt built his Church upon his Faith; yet denied, and that with execration, his Lord and gracious Redeemer: nay, all Chriſt's Diſciples (though at one time they forſook all to follow him, yet at another time) they all forſooke him and fled. But, why ſhould I thus diſcover my Father's nakedneſſe? rather (indeed) would I goe backward and cover the ſame with the mantle of my pity: Yet, let us not be too laviſh in pitying them; For, God hath cauſed their infirmities to be recorded:</p>
            <p>Firſt, to let us underſtand that both they and we have one and the ſame God, who was alwaies offended with ſinne, were the Perſons that wrought it never ſo great or glorious.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to let us know that both they and we have one and the ſame Phyſician to cure us of all our maladies, <hi>viz:</hi> the imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, who <hi>ſaveth his People from their ſinnes, Mat.</hi> 1.21.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, to teach us circumſpection and cautelouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to flie from ſinne as from a Scrpent, and to ſay to it as <hi>Pharach</hi> ſaid to <hi>Moſes, See that thou ſee my face no more;</hi> or as <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Lot, If thou go on the right hand I will goe on the left, or if thou go on the left hand, I will go on the right:</hi> For, if the deare Children of God, who have gone before us both in time, and in the graces of the Spirit beare ſuch reproach, by reaſon their corruptions are regiſtred; what ſhall we ſuſtaine, who live in a brighter Age, and upon whom the ends of the world are come?</p>
            <p>But, (alas!) ſo baſe is our nature that ſinne will be a Jebuſite; it will be a conſtant gueſt to our houſe, though it ſitteth not in the chiefeſt room; it is bred in the bone, and it will not out of the fleſh, untill <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s bones be carried out of <hi>Aegypt, (i. e.)</hi> untill we be out of this world. As <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not paſſe to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but through the Deſart of <hi>Zin:</hi> ſo we muſt not look to paſſe to our ſpirituall <hi>Canaan,</hi> but through the wilderneſſe of ſinne. Sinnes are like Rebels, that not onely revolt, but alſo keep caſtle againſt their Soveraigne, from whence they are not eaſily removed. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> tells us of three things that doe acquire wiſdome, <hi>viz:</hi> Nature, Learning, and Exerciſe: Sure I am, not theſe; but God's free grace can make us avoid ſinne. Philoſophers are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that if the inferiour ſpheres were not governed and ſtayed by the higheſt, the ſwiftneſſe of their motion would quickly fire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97183:8"/>the world: So I may very well hold, that if the affections of God's deareſt Children were not moderated by the guidance of his holy Spirit, they would run ſo farre into ſinne, as to precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate their ſoules into the black gulfe of eternall deſtruction; for, our reaſon is no better than treaſon, and our affections are no better than infections. We cannot truely ſay of our ſelves as <hi>Iſidore</hi> too boldly of himſelfe; For fourty yeares ſpace (ſaith he) I found not in my ſelfe any ſinne, no, not ſo much as in thought, anger, or any inordinate deſire: or, as <hi>Alexander de Hales</hi> of <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> His life was ſo upright, (ſaith he) that <hi>Adam</hi> ſeemed not to have ſinned in him. No, no, (my Brethren) look upon a Chriſtian, at the beſt, whilſt he liveth in this world, and you may well compare him unto the Arke of the Covanant, which was but a cubit and half high, an imperfect meaſure, by this you may know his ſtature; adde what you will, it will be but a cubit and an half: Perfectly imperfect was he, when he began; imperfectly perfect when he ends in all his actions. Therefore (as we doe offend in many things) let us in humility and ſincerity of heart acknowledge and confeſſe the ſame, (as Saint <hi>James</hi> in my Text) <hi>In many things we doe offend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath been the conſtant practiſe of God's beloved ones: <hi>What is man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eliphaz) that he ſhould be cleane? and he that is borne of woman that he ſhould be juſt? Behold, God found no ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe in his Saints: yea, the heavens are not cleane in his ſight, Job</hi> 15.14, 15. Therefore <hi>Job</hi> acknowledgeth his failings, <hi>Job</hi> 7.20. and when he came to plead with God for his uprightneſſe, did abhorre himſelfe, and repented in duſt and aſhes, <hi>Job</hi> 42.6. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> maketh a large confeſſion of his own and the Peoples ſinnes, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.5, 6, 7. So <hi>Ezra,</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the behalf of the People, confeſſe that juſtice belongeth to God; but ſhame and confuſion to themſelves, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.5, 6, 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.6, 7. <hi>Salomon</hi> hath his Booke of Acknowledgment, <hi>viz: Eccleſiaſtes. David</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his folly in numbering the People, ſaying, <hi>I have ſinned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly in that I have done, therefore now Lord, I beſeech thee, take away the treſpaſſe of thy Servant: for I have done very fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. He confeſſeth likewiſe his Adultery with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s Wife, and his Murder, in cauſing her innocent Husband to be ſlaine: And for theſe he is content (if I may ſo ſpeake) to doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97183:9"/>penance every Lords-day in our Congregations where his <hi>Pſalms</hi> are preached, read, or ſung: For, in how many <hi>Pſalmes</hi> hath he recorded his offences with his owne hand! Thoſe that came to <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> to be Baptized of him, <hi>came confeſſing their ſinnes, Matth.</hi> 3.6. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Goe from me for I am a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I doe not the good thing, which I would; but the evill which I would not, that doe I, Rom.</hi> 7.19. Nay further, Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith, that <hi>we ſinne, in ſaying we have no ſinne,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay that we have no ſinne, we deceive our ſelves, and there is no truth in us.</hi> But (peradventure) ſome will object and ſay, doth not the ſame Apoſtle averre, (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. part of 8, &amp; 9. <hi>v.</hi>) that <hi>he who committeth ſinne is of the Devill? And whoſoever is borne of God ſinneth not: for his ſeed remaineth in him, neither can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God?</hi> I ſhall anſwer briefly, <hi>To com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne</hi> ſignifieth, not ſimply to ſinne: It importeth not a mixt action, wherein the Sinner is partly willing, partly unwilling; but an abſolute reſigning of that faculty for the performance of wicked deſignes. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he which doth ſettle and ſet himſelf to worke wickedneſſe, is of the Devil: But, <hi>he that is borne of God ſinneth not, nor can ſinne:</hi> that is, doth not, nor can indulge or cocker his ſinne; the one is tranſported by his owne rebellious will; the other inforced by urgent neceſſity: the one is carried forward by a prompt and peremptory inclination; the other by violent &amp; coactive temptation: the former ſinneth of a premedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate mind; the latter by conſtraint: doe what we can, whilſt we carry about this maſſe of corruption, ſinne will have its reſidence in us, even in the beſt of us; but we will not ſuffer it to reigne in our mortall bodies, that we ſhould obey it in the luſts thereof. If it violently overrule us, we will not willingly let it rule over us: If therefore a poore Sinner can ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. I would not willingly doe <hi>that evill which I doe; It is the law of my members that rebelleth againſt the law of my mind, and leadeth me captive to the law of ſinne,</hi> he may look with comfort towards the Mercy-ſeat. For, <hi>Peccata non nocent,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Jerome) ſi non placent,</hi> Our ſinnes ſhall not hurt us, if they doe diſpleaſe us; for, <hi>in many things we doe offend,</hi>—</p>
            <p>But, why doth not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>we</hi> offend in a few things, but in many things, and why in many things, and not in all things,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97183:9"/>or every thing? It is reſolved in a word, <hi>We</hi> offend, not in a few, but many things; becauſe we have not a few, but many ſubtile, malitious, vigilant, ſtrong enemies; and, not the leaſt, is our owne inbred corruption: <hi>We</hi> offend, not in all things, or every thing; becauſe the grace of God ſupporteth us, and his grace is ſufficient for us, for by grace are <hi>we</hi> ſaved, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5. In the beſt of God's Children there is Nature, Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> which makes them to offend <hi>in many things.</hi> Againe, there is in them Grace, Regeneration, and the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> which makes them, not to offend in all things. If <hi>we</hi> thinke, that <hi>we</hi> are too weake by nature to reſiſt and vanquiſh ſinne; let us comfortably aſſure our ſelves, that by grace <hi>we</hi> ſhall be Victors; yea, <hi>more: than Conquerours,</hi> through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath ſo freely and dearly loved us. The fleſh, or the nature of man (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.) luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh, ſo that <hi>we</hi> cannot doe as <hi>we</hi> would: If <hi>we</hi> would ſerve God, ſo holily, cheerfully, and conſtantly, as the Angels in heaven, <hi>we</hi> cannot, becauſe the fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit: If againe <hi>we</hi> would ſinne with full conſent of will, ſo brutiſhly as the wicked doe, <hi>we</hi> cannot, becauſe the ſpirit luſteth againſt the fleſh. Let us therefore implore this ſpirit of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and let us beſeech the Almighty to drive the <hi>Zanzum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mims,</hi> our ſinnes out of the land of our hearts by the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of his grace. It is ſaid, that <hi>Hercules</hi> led <hi>Cerberus</hi> in a leaſe: Oh! let us pray to God to give us power and victory over our mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, deformed ſinnes, that they may not command <hi>us;</hi> but <hi>we</hi> them: And, if at any time <hi>we</hi> be overtaken in a fault, let our hearts ſmite us immediately; let us crie to God earneſtly for his pardoning, preventing, and perſevering grace. Alas! what is our life? is it not as it were a Booke? our birth is the Title-page, our baptiſme the Epiſtle Dedicatory, our groanes and cryings the Epiſtle to the Reader, our childhood is the Argument and Contents of the whole enſuing Treatiſe, our life and actions are the Subject, our ſinnes and errours are the Faults eſcaped; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let our repentance be the Correction; let not us think our ſelves <hi>too good</hi> for the office; for, even <hi>we</hi> are Offenders. Again, let us not turne <hi>ego</hi> into <hi>ille,</hi> or <hi>nos</hi> into <hi>vos;</hi> let us not look upon the offences of <hi>others,</hi> and forget our <hi>owne.</hi> The Cock clapt his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97183:10"/>wings firſt to his own ſides and awoke himſelf, before he crowed to awaken <hi>Peter;</hi> ſo let us ſay to our ſelves, <hi>we</hi> have offended, before we ſay to others, <hi>ye</hi> have offended. It had been good for <hi>Narciſſus, ut non viderat ipſe,</hi> that <hi>he</hi> had not ſeen himſelfe; but our greateſt happineſſe would be in ſeeing our ſelves. Let us not be Mole-eyed towards our ſelves, and Eagle-eyed towards our Brethren, and ſo turne <hi>Chriſt's, Sed vos pro vobis,</hi> into <hi>Virgils Sic vos non vobis.</hi> Let us not be like <hi>Crates Thebanus,</hi> who is called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Dore-opener;</hi> becauſe he uſed to ruſh into every mans houſe (as our Engliſh-H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>drivers did alate) and there to find fault with whatſoever was amiſſe. let us not ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> did of <hi>John, Hic autem quid?</hi> What ſhall this man doe? as one carefull of other mens Eſtates: But, let us ſay, <hi>Domine! quis ego ſum?</hi> Lord! what am I? <hi>Domine! miſerere mei peccatoris,</hi> Lord! be mercifull to me a Sinner. Laſtly, let us, who offend in many things, beware that we want not one thing, namely, a thankfull heart to him, who will not ſuffer us to offend in all things; but (notwithſtanding our many offences) will acknowledge us for his owne, guide and governe us with his grace in this world, and receive us into glory in the world to come. <hi>In many things we doe offend;</hi> nay, more, <hi>In many things we offend [all:]</hi> which brings me to the laſt Particular, <hi>viz:</hi> the Delinquents, deſcribed by their Generallity, <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not ſaid <hi>Ye all;</hi> but <hi>We all:</hi> Here is One, and All; Many, and All; yea, Saints, and All: For, We All are under this <hi>black Rod.</hi> Would a <hi>Committee-man,</hi> a <hi>Colonel,</hi> a <hi>Generall,</hi> aſſume to himſelfe ſuch a word of charge, and ſuch a chargeable word as this? No ſurely, though a <hi>Cobler:</hi> Yet, the word is generall, and (for ought I know) belongeth to a <hi>Generall:</hi> But, ſhall I ſay, to a <hi>Thomas,</hi> who would not believe his <hi>Maſter?</hi> Nay, rather to a bleſſed <hi>Saint, (viz:</hi> Saint <hi>James</hi>) who died (though a <hi>Biſhop</hi>) for the honour of his <hi>Maſter, Quis non contremiſcat</hi> (faith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin) cum Apoſtolus dicit</hi> [Omnes?] <hi>non offenditis, ſed offendimus?</hi> Who cannot but tremble, like the heartleſſe Deer, to heare the Apoſtle pronounce this impartiall word <hi>[All?]</hi> and not <hi>ye all,</hi> but <hi>we all</hi> offend? Tremble then we muſt; for, the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> hath his <hi>Nos omnes</hi> too; <hi>All we, like Sheepe, have gone aſtray; we have, every one, turned to our owne way,</hi> Eſay 53.6. And, <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97183:10"/>eſt more peccandum errare;</hi> to ſinne is to goe out of our way, like ſilly Cattle, Sheep eſpecially. Moreover, this <hi>[All]</hi> pricketh, not onely the <hi>Church Militant,</hi> which is <hi>inviſible;</hi> but that part alſo, which is <hi>viſible:</hi> For, <hi>à meliori ad pejus valet ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum:</hi> If <hi>Aaron</hi> maketh a molten Calfe, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> will worſhip it: If the <hi>Commanders</hi> plunder, the <hi>common Souldiers</hi> will ſteale: If the <hi>Babes of grace</hi> will depoſe their KING, the <hi>graceleſſe</hi> Babes will murther Him: If <hi>black Saints</hi> have their aberrations, <hi>white Devils</hi> will have their tranſgreſſions; <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am cleane from ſinne?</hi> Prov. 20.9. <hi>Surely, there is no man juſt on the earth, that doeth good, and ſinneth not,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.22. <hi>There is no man that ſinneth not,</hi> 2 Chron. 6.36. Wherefore the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth ingenuouſly acknowledge her black hue and ſwart complexion, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5. And, the <hi>Fathers</hi> doe commonly compare her to the <hi>Moone,</hi> and well may they doe ſo, in reſpect of her borrowed light, and ſpotted face: All the beames which ſhe reflecteth to the world, are darted upon her by the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, and yet by reaſon of her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall temper, in her brighteſt ſhining, ſhe appeareth ſpotty. As a faire face, hath a wart; a goodly pomgranate, a rotten kernell; good wine, lees and dregs; the Sunne, his eclipſe; the Moone, her ſpots: So the viſible Church of Chriſt hath her imperfections and faults: And that too, both in reſpect of 1 Doctrine, and 2 Converſation. <hi>We know but in part,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. <hi>When the Sonne of Man commeth, ſhall he find faith on earth?</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.8. Againe, for her Converſation, ſhe is like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s party coloured ſheep: there will be a ſpeckled breed, ſo long as the flocks caſt their eyes on motly vanities, in the gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this world. There will be tares amongſt the wheat, in the ſame field: chaffe with the corne, on the ſame floore, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12. good fiſh and bad in the ſame net, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.47. And <hi>all,</hi> even <hi>we all</hi> do offend in many things. Was not Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> blinded with the opinion of Free-will, and <hi>Peter's</hi> Supremacy? did not Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> hold Rebaptization? did not <hi>Origen</hi> maintaine Univerſall ſalvation of Men and Devils? did not Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> write doubtfully about Purgatory, and for a while held confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently that Children could not be ſaved without the Lord's Supper? Did not Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> maintaine Virginity above
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97183:11"/>Marriage? Did not <hi>Tertullian</hi> believe ſecond Marriage unlawfull? <hi>Illiricus</hi> fail about Originall ſin? And <hi>Luther</hi> about Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation? <hi>Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. Yea, whole Churches have offended in matters of Faith, and good Manners. The <hi>Galatians</hi> erred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Juſtification: The <hi>Corinthians</hi> about the Reſurrection: The <hi>Romanes, Coloſſians</hi> and <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> had haughty ſpirits, brabling Sophiſters, and brethren that walked diſorderly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.2.16. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.8. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15.9.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. Were not the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> faulty? <hi>Jezebel</hi> prevailed in <hi>Thyatira; Sardis</hi> had a name without <hi>life; Pergamus</hi> was tainted with <hi>Baaliſme;</hi> and <hi>Laodicea</hi> with <hi>luke-warmneſſe;</hi> and <hi>Epheſus</hi> had forſaken her <hi>firſt Love.</hi> And doth it not appeare, that the viſible and glorious Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem, Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> have grievouſly erred and offended, if we looke upon the Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, Hereſies and Atheiſme now raigning there?</p>
            <p>And God (doubtleſſe) permitteth theſe offences and errours in his Church, that the Elect might be imployed and tried; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates left unexcuſable; Gods ſtrength appeare in our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and his mercy and juſtice in ſuch variety of objects; For, <hi>The beſt of us all doe offend in many things:</hi> And are not we (think ye) much bound to our <hi>Proto parents</hi> for this our fraile and weak condition? Surely, their unlawfull deſire of knowledge, brought upon them, and us all, ſo black ignorance, as that <hi>we know nothing</hi> (as we ought to know) <hi>Job</hi> 8.9. But we ſee things, <hi>per tranſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> or, <hi>rimulam,</hi> or (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) <hi>darkly, as in a glaſſe.</hi> Can we truly ſay (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſometimes) the image of God is neither deceaſed, nor decreaſed in us? Or, (as moſt of the <hi>Schoole-men</hi>) though the actuall image is decayed in us, yet the aptitudinall doth remaine? Place the image of God where you will: If in the Faculties, the Underſtanding is obſcured, and the Will oppoſite: In the Appetite? that is diſtracted: In ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall graces? thoſe are defaced. Well (therefore) may we conclude with <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> Though there be not an extinction of it in any part, yet there is an inquination in all. Yea, in a word, <hi>Man being in honour regarded not, but became like the Beaſts that periſh: The Fathers have eaten ſowre grapes, and the Childrens teeth are ſet on edge:</hi> Or rather, their ſweet meate hath proved unto us ſowre ſawce: Our firſt Parents, with a ſhort breakfaſt,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97183:11"/>have brought a ſurfet upon us all, their Poſterity, whereof they cannot recover ſo long as they doe breath under earths ſpangled Canopie: None but Chriſt Jeſus alone was free from ſinne, who was, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>God-man:</hi> For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doe <hi>all we</hi> offend in many things? Then juſtly may we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne many who offend (ſhall I ſay, in great things; in the greateſt things?) even in all things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a generation as darke as Hell; yet, too too viſible in our Climate: How many Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> have we amongſt us, who feare not God, no, nor reverence man; though Gods <hi>Vicegerent,</hi> and their lawfull <hi>Soveraigne!</hi> How many curſed, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious <hi>Shebaes,</hi> blowing the tumultuous Trumpets of Rebellion, and ſaying, we have no part in CHARLES, nor inheritance in the Sonne of JAMES; every man to his Tents, <hi>O England!</hi> How many <hi>Sacrilegious Baltaſars, Plundering Achans, Heart-burning Sauls, Covetous Nabals, Oppreſſing Ahabs, Whoriſh Jezebels, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing Demaſſes, Fratricideous Cains, Regicideous Jehues, Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty Nimrods, Malicious Doegs, Backbiting Ziba</hi>'s, <hi>Curſing Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi>'s, <hi>Scoffing Chams,</hi> and <hi>Prophane Eſaus!</hi> I ſay againe, Oh how many! The Eccho anſwers, Many. And theſe are blacke, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhew of the contrary, to a diſcerning eye: Short of <hi>Agrippa,</hi> not worthy to be termed, <hi>ſeeming Chriſtians:</hi> Corrupt are they, and abominable in their doings, drinking iniquity like water, and ſinning as it were with Cart-ropes: Yea, <hi>they have ſold themſelves to worke wickedneſſe in the ſight of the Lord,</hi> and in the ſight of men: There is no feare of God, nor ſhame of men, before their eies: They have made falſhood their refuge, and under ungodlineſſe are they hid: Therefore ſhall the Lord raine upon them ſnares, fire and brimſtone, this ſhall be their portion to drinke: yea, the Lord ſhall bring upon them deſtruction; yea, the Lord our God ſhall deſtroy them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe, there are a ſort of People whoſe waies may ſeem right, even to a good Man: but their waies are the waies of death: Our Saviour calls them, painted Sepulchers, <hi>Sepulchra, quaſi ſemi-ſepulchra, exterius nitida, interius foetida,</hi> faire without, and foule within. They are like unto Apothecaries Galli-pots, <hi>quorum tituli remedium habent, pixides venenum,</hi> without they have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97183:12"/>the title of ſome excellent preſervative; but within, they are full of deadly aconite. Without, they are <hi>Catoes;</hi> within, <hi>Neroes:</hi> heart them, no men better; ſearch and trie them, no men worſe: they will have <hi>Jacob</hi>'s voice, but <hi>Eſau</hi>'s hand: Outwardly they will be <hi>John,</hi> but inwardly they will be <hi>Herod:</hi> They profeſſe like <hi>Saints,</hi> but practiſe like <hi>Sathans:</hi> they have their long Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but their ſhort preyings. Counterfeit holineſſe is their cloake for all manner of Villanies, and the Mid-wife to bring forth their ſubtilties. The <hi>Eagle</hi> ſoareth on high, not to flie to heaven; but to gaine her prey upon earth: So, many doe carry a great deale of ſeeming devotion, and lift up their eyes towards heaven; but they doe it, onely to accompliſh with the more eaſe, ſafety, and applauſe, their wicked and damnable deſignes here on earth. But let ſuch know, that <hi>ſimulata ſanctitas, duplex iniquitas,</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit holineſſe is double iniquity; and our Saviour denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Eight woes againſt Hypocrites in <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. Neither (to my preſent remembrance) could I ever find that he converted any ſuch. <hi>Are thy hands full of blood? make thy many prayers then and ſee if God will heare thee in the day of thy calamity. Iſa.</hi> 1.15. He that regardeth iniquity in his heart God will not heare; his very prayers and all his outward acts of devotion, in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, ſhall be turned into ſinne unto him.</p>
            <p>Thou doſt faſt (perhaps) but is it to ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe? Thou doſt give Almes to the poore (peradventure) ſometimes: Thou commeſt to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper; but is thy heart all this while ſwolne with ambition, covetouſneſs, envy, hatred &amp; malice? aſſure thy ſelf thy ſacrifice is not accepted; for, God will have mercy, and not ſacrifice; to doe this is but as the chopping off a Dogges necke. Thou pretendeſt a reformation, but thou wilt have it purchaſed by bloody and unlawfull meanes: Mark therefore what the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Mic.</hi> 3.10, 11, 12. <hi>They build up Zion with blood, and Jeruſalem with iniquity. The Heads thereof judge for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and the Prieſts thereof teach for hire, and the Prophets thereof propheſy for money; yet, will they leane upon the Lord, and ſay, Is not the Lord amongst us? no evill can come upon us. Therefore ſhall Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for your ſake, be plowed as a field, and Jeruſalem ſhall be an heap; and the mountaine of the houſe, as the high places of the forreſt.</hi> To
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97183:12"/>build up <hi>Zion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was (doubtleſſe) an acceptable work unto the Lord: but to doe it with blood, injuſtice, and lies, was ſo deteſtable unto him, that he threatens an utter deſolation to both <hi>Zion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for their ſakes. Well then, if we finde theſe Wolves in Sheep-skins, let us (if we can) hang them up; for they are, and will be Wolves ſtill: Sinne they will, and that with a witneſſe: Yea, let us pray, that theſe many black and white Devils, who offend in all things, may be cut off; that we all, who offend in many things, may not offend in any thing: For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But doe we all continually offend in many things? And ſhall we doe ſo till death? What may we then thinke of thoſe fanatick ſpirits, who doe aſcribe, judgement, without errour; and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, without ſinne, unto the moſt ſinfull Sonnes and Daughters of men? Surely, from what we have already heard, we may truly confute, and juſtly condemne the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (that <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi>) for aſſuming to her ſelfe ſuch a garment of purity and infallibility, as to merit and ſuperarrogate Heaven; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhe hath not left her Whoriſh tricks, but ſtill brings forth uncleane Children, of an uncleane ſeed; her infallibility failing, and her purity being impure; that man of ſinne, <hi>viz:</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> (ſay ſome of their owne Writers) cannot ſinne, erre, or offend: But, this being openly and apparently falſe; for ſome of their <hi>Popes</hi> have beene <hi>Conjurers, Sorcerers</hi> and <hi>Inchanters, Adulterers, Murtherers, Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> yea (in a word) their <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, Nocents;</hi> their <hi>Benedicts, Maledicts;</hi> their <hi>Bonifaces, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifaces, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore (I ſay) their <hi>Jeſuites</hi> of late have found out a ſubtile diſtinction, <hi>viz:</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> may ſinne, erre and offend in his owne perſon, as a man, <hi>ſed non quatenus Papa,</hi> but not ſo farre forth as he is <hi>Pope, è Cathedrâ,</hi> to define and teach errours. Although we may grant it to be a ſubtile diſtinction, yet not a ſolid one; for if the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot guide his owne faith, how can it be expected that he ſhould guide the faith of the Church? The rule muſt not onely make ſtrait that which is croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but it muſt be ſtrait it ſelfe. Moreover, theſe Romaniſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be blamed, for affirming, that the bleſſed Virgin was pure from all ſinne, both Originall, and Actuall: Their words are theſe; <hi>Our Lady never ſinned; our Lady never ſinned ſo much
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97183:13"/>as venially in all her life; ſhe exactly fulfilled every tittle of the whole Law,</hi> that is, ſhe was without ſinne. That ſhe was not ſo great a Sinner as the reſt of Gods Children, I doe with humble acknowledgment believe; but, that ſhe was without ſinne, her owne expreſſion declares the contrary, in that ſhe ſaid, <hi>my ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour:</hi> If <hi>Chriſt</hi> was her <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſhe muſt of neceſſity be a Sinner.</p>
            <p>Well may likewiſe the <hi>Manichees, Catheriſts,</hi> or <hi>Puritanes,</hi> be condemned, who (as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> writeth) avouched, That they neither had ſinned, nor could ſinne; becauſe they were trees of righteouſneſſe, and a good tree (ſaid they) cannot bring forth evill fruit: Therefore we cannot ſee how we ſhould ſinne even in thought. Likewiſe the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who dreamed themſelves to be ſo perfect as by their perfection to juſtifie other men, as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> telleth us. Alſo, the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> and <hi>Family of Love;</hi> for they were of opinion, that they were ſo free from ſinne, as that they needed not, neither would they vouchſafe to ſay that Petition in the <hi>Lords Prayer, Forgive us our treſpaſſes,</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> teſtifyeth, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cont. Petil. c.</hi> 14.) Moreover, the <hi>Adamites,</hi> who deemed themſelves as pure as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah</hi> were before their Fall, (as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> averreth.) And the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Carpocratiant,</hi> who blaſphemouſly belched out of their black mouthes and ſulpherous breaths, that they were as holy as <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> himſelfe, (as <hi>Ireneus</hi> affirmeth, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24.) I might here point out unto you many more ſinful-ſinleſſe <hi>Juſtitiaries,</hi> as the <hi>Novatians, Jovinians, Enthuſiaſts, Antinomiſts, Browniſts, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowiſts, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Millenaries:</hi> But, it is not my deſire to lead you any longer in theſe crooked paths; for whoſoever walketh in them ſhall not know peace: neither will I detaine you in the barren wilderneſſe of vaine man's phariſaicall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, where you may (doubtleſſe) be ſcratcht and torne with thornes and briers: Rather will I bring you into a ſpecious gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den where you may have choice of fragrant flowers for your owne utility and conſolation. Seeing then, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi debita conſideratio?</hi> Where is our due conſideration? Have all Gods deare Children their frailties and deviations? Is his Church viſible and inviſible poſſeſſed with an <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97183:13"/>leads out of the way? Are his choſen, ſubject to many aberra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and tranſgreſſions? And ſhall not <hi>we,</hi> even <hi>all we</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who were ſometimes members of the moſt glorious, and envied <hi>Church</hi> in the Chriſtian World, <hi>Search and trie our waies and turne unto the Lord our God? Gather your ſelves, even gather you, O Nation not worthy to be beloved, before the decree come forth, and ye be as chaffe, that paſſeth in a day, and before the fierce wrath of the Lord come upon you, and before the day of the Lords anger come upon you, Zeph.</hi> 2.1, 2. Let me ſpeak to all the <hi>Tribes</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to all the ſtates and conditions of <hi>England;</hi> to you of <hi>Judah,</hi> the <hi>Princes;</hi> to you of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> the <hi>Counſellours;</hi> to you of <hi>Aſſur,</hi> the <hi>Merchants;</hi> and to you of <hi>Levi,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts:</hi> yea, to you all of what ranke or quality ſoever. Let me aske you, Have not all of you offended? nay, doe not ye ſtill offend in many things? If not, what meaneth the lowing of the Oxen, and the bleating of the Sheep? What may we underſtand by thoſe ſtrong cries which aſcend up to heaven for vengeance to fall downe upon us? You that turne <hi>Bethel</hi> into <hi>Beth-aven,</hi> the houſe of <hi>God</hi> into a den of Thieves: You, that rob the <hi>Levites</hi> of their portion, devouring whole Churches, Steeples and all, and have the bells jingling at your heeles, doe not ye offend? You, that cauſe judgement, and juſtice to grow up as hemlock in the furrowes of the field, doe not ye offend? You that take darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe; bitter for ſweet, and ſweet for bitter: You that have ſpoken words, ſwearing falſly in making a Covenant: You that ſwore to make your KING glorious, the richeſt <hi>Prince</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> to be feared abroad and to be loved at home: You, that declared and proteſted, that you did not fight againſt the Power and Perſon of the KING, onely againſt his evill <hi>Councell:</hi> You likewiſe that declared, [calling heaven and earth to record of your reall intentions] that you would re-inthrone Him and reſtore Him to His juſt Rights, have not ye offended? For, doth not he, that provoketh him to anger (onely) ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his owne ſoule? You, who (through ambition) have trod upon the <hi>Crowne,</hi> and trampled upon the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and would not be ſubject to ſuperiority: You, who (through covetouſneſſe) have ſequeſtred, and plundered mens Eſtates, and (to fill your unſatiable deſires) have been prodigall in ſhedding your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97183:14"/>blood: Let me aske (I pray) have not you offended? nay, do not you ſtill offend? Let me aske you of the <hi>Parliament</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſſembly;</hi> Have not you offended <hi>God,</hi> your <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> this whole <hi>Nation,</hi> &amp; your own <hi>Conſciences?</hi> ſhall I ſay in doing no good, or rather, in doing hurt? ſhall I doubt, ye have been the Chief Inſtruments, to bring upon us, and your ſelves (through <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum</hi>) all the <hi>Interjections</hi> of woe and lamentation?</p>
            <p>Have not Councels erred and offended, even in matters of faith? Was it not ordained by a Councell, that if any man did confeſſe that Jeſus was the Chriſt, he ſhould be excommunicate? Was there not a Councell gathered to ſuppreſſe Chriſt and his Doctrine? Did not a Councell conſult how they might take Jeſus by ſubtilty and kill him? Did not a Councell ſeek for falſe Witneſſe to put him to Death? Was not Jeſus bound, led away, and delivered to <hi>Pilate</hi> by a Councell? A Councell judged our Saviour to be both a Deceiver and a Blaſphemer. A Councell corrupted the Souldiers, and willed them to tell a lie. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were withſtood by a Councell, and not ſuffered to preach. And a Councell cauſed the Apoſtles to be beaten. Arrianiſme was confirmed by the Councell of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> as Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> affirmeth. The Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> made the Traditions and workes of fraile ſinfull Men equivalent to the ſacred Scriptures. The ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> eſtabliſhed the adoration of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> clipt the wings of the prerogative of Princes to advance the Pope and Clergy above them. I might mention many more, beſides the Councels that have been of our owne Nation in our owne Kingdome from time to time: let it ſuffice, that the conſideration of theſe things ought to make us believe and embrace nothing ordained by Men, unleſſe the ſame be conſonant and agreeable to the word of God. I am ſure Saint <hi>Hilarie</hi> (well weighing the premiſes) in his Epiſtle to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> calls the Synod of <hi>Mediolane, The Malignant Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue:</hi> And <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> (in his 42 <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Procopius</hi>) open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pronounced, that, He never ſaw any good end of a Councell. They are (ordinarily) like <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s figgs, If good, very good; if bad, very bad. Let us therefore, in the towring thoughts of our owne purity and infallibility, looke downe upon the black feet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97183:14"/>of our frailty and infirmity: For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, doth Saint <hi>James</hi> acknowledge this? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi cenfeſſle noſtra?</hi> where is our confeſſion? We decline ſinne through all the caſes, (ſaith one witily:) In the <hi>Nominative,</hi> by <hi>Pride;</hi> in the <hi>Genetive,</hi> by <hi>Luxury;</hi> in the <hi>Dative,</hi> by <hi>Simonie;</hi> in the <hi>Accuſative,</hi> by <hi>Detraction;</hi> in the <hi>Vocative,</hi> by <hi>Adulation;</hi> in the <hi>Ablative,</hi> by <hi>Extortion:</hi> And ſhall we not acknowledge them, in any caſe? <hi>God</hi> gave ſhame for ſinne, and boldneſſe for confeſſion; and, when ſinne is committed, ſhall ſhame be abſent? and, when it ſhould be confeſt, ſhall ſhame be preſent? Shall we be like unto the <hi>Elephant,</hi> who will not drinke of cleer water in the limpid fountaine, leſt he ſhould ſee his deformity? or, like old <hi>Gentle-women</hi> growne out of date, who will not trouble themſelves to behold their faces in a glaſſe, becauſe (they know) they ſhall ſee nothing better than hollow eyes, paſe cheeks, and a wrimkled countenance? Doe we all offend in many things, and ſhall we hide our ſelves from the light, and ſay we offend not in any thing? Let <hi>God</hi> be True, and every Man a Liar, as it is written. Let us not hide our ſinnes, either by excuſing them, with <hi>Aaron, Exod.</hi> 32.24. or by colouring them with faire pretenſes and diſtinctions, as the <hi>Jewes. Jer.</hi> 22.14. or as <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.20, 21. Or by tranſlating them from our ſelves, and laying the blame upon others, as <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> the 3. Or by defending them, or by extenuating them, or laſtly, by denying them, as the <hi>Harlot, Prov.</hi> 20.30. Let us not ſay, as thoſe in Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>'s dayes, <hi>Non feci; ſi feci, non malè feci; ſi malè feci, non multum malè; ſi multum malè, non malâ intentione; ſi malâ intentione, tamen alienâ perſuaſione.</hi> I did it not; if I did it, I did it not ill in doing it; If I did ill in doing it, not very ill; If very ill, not with an ill intent; If with an ill intent, it was by another's perſwaſion. But let us, with <hi>David,</hi> ingenuouſly acknowledge our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and let our ſinns be ever before us: For, there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion without confeſſion, but upon our confeſſion <hi>God</hi> will forgive. <hi>Deus tegat vulnera, noli tu</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.) <hi>Si tu tegere volueris, embeſcens medicus non curabit,</hi> Let God hide thy wounds, doe not thou; if thou wilt needs hide them, the Chirurgeon, as one aſhamed at thy folly, will not cure thee. God will not poure in the balme of his mercy till we let
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97183:15"/>out our corruption by confeſſion. <hi>God,</hi> with <hi>Eliſha,</hi> demands veſſels empty with confeſſion before he will come in. If we ſet our ſinnes in order before our faces, <hi>God</hi> will caſt them behind his back; but, if we caſt them behind our backs, <hi>God</hi> will ſet them before his face. If we remember them, <hi>God</hi> will forget them: If we forget them, <hi>God</hi> will remember them. <hi>Solvit criminum nexus, verecunda confeſſio peccatorum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de penit.</hi> the knot of our ſinnes is looſed by an humble confeſſion of them. <hi>Ipſa agnitio culpae eſt impetratio veniae,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bern. cap.</hi> 11. <hi>Med.</hi> the acknowledgment of the fault, doth impetrate pardon. <hi>If we confeſſe our ſinnes</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9.) <hi>God is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and juſt to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe.</hi> It was a very eaſie phyſick which the Man of <hi>God</hi> preſcribed unto <hi>Naaman,</hi> (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.10.) <hi>viz:</hi> to go and waſh ſeven times in the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> and to be cleanſed from his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie: And ſurely (my Beloved) we may ſtand and wonder at <hi>this,</hi> if our leproſie were not as ill; nay, worſe, by how much the ſoule is better than the body: yet, we have the ſame phyſick preſcribed, onely confeſſe, and be cleane. Yea, (ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 32.5.) <hi>I ſaid I will confeſſe my ſinne, and thou forgaveſt the puniſhment of my ſinne.</hi> Note, that this ſpeech of the Prophet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies two things: Firſt, the difficulty of the act of confeſſion; it muſt not be done hand over head, but upon due deliberation, and ſerious conſideration. <hi>[I ſaid I will.]</hi> Secondly, <hi>God</hi>'s readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to forgive: I did but ſay, that I would confeſſe, and thou forgaveſt: <hi>Nondum pronunciat, ſed ſolùm promittit, &amp; Deus dimit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> upon the place. As yet he utters not his confeſſion, but onely promiſeth to doe it, and God accepts. As yet the word is not in his mouth that man may heare his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but <hi>God</hi> heareth and receiveth him into favour. Oh therefore (deare Brethren) let us aſcend up into the Tribunall of our mind, even againſt our ſelves, and place our ſelves guilty before our ſelves, that <hi>God</hi> may place us before him. For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, is our condition thus tranſgreſſive, and therefore deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi tùm Patientia noſtra?</hi> Where is then our Patience? When <hi>Samuel</hi> told <hi>Eli</hi> from the mouth of God, that the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his houſe ſhould not be purged with <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> or <hi>burnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offering,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97183:15"/>for ever; he anſwered both meekly and patiently, <hi>It is the Lord, let him doe what ſeemeth to him good,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.18. When <hi>David</hi>'s Sonne, even rebellious <hi>Abſalom,</hi> conſpired to take his Fathers Crowne from his head, and his head from his ſhoulders; <hi>David</hi> fled from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with this patheticall and patient reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.25, 26.) <hi>If I ſhall finde favour in the eies of the Lord, he will bring me againe, and ſhew me both it, and the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle thereof: But, if he ſay thus, I have no delight in thee: Behold, here am I, let him doe to me as ſeemeth good in his eies.</hi> When <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Gera</hi> came out, and curſed, ſaying, <hi>Come forth, come forth, thou man of blood, and man of Belial: The Lord hath brought upon thee all the blood of the houſe of Saul, &amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7, 8. What ſaid <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> who would have cut off this <hi>Miſcreants</hi> head, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Behold, my Sonne, which came of mine owne bowels, ſeeketh my life: then how much more may this Sonne of Jemini? Suffer him to curſe, for the Lord hath bidden him: It may be the Lord will looke on my tears, and doe me good for his curſing this day.</hi> And marvell not to heare him thus ſpeaking, when you throughly weigh that ingenuous acknowledgement of his (in <hi>Pſalme</hi> the 119.75.) ſaying, <hi>I know thy judgements are right, and thou haſt afflicted me juſtly. Job</hi> upon the conſideration of this, in the depth of his miſery, would not mount up ſo high as to plead with his Maker, and contend with his puniſhments Inflictour; but laid his hand upon his mouth, and would not open it, unleſſe to ſay, <hi>Though thou killeſt me, yet will I truſt in thee:</hi> And, <hi>I abhor my ſelf, and repent in duſt and aſhes.</hi> Our ſtripes are not according to our ſins; for, if God ſhould beat us with as many rods, as we have grieved him with ſinnes, he ſhould adde yet ten times more to our greateſt afflictions: We goe aſtray like ſheep; ſhall we barke or bleate, when God ſends forth his dogge <hi>(affliction)</hi> to bring us home againe? Will the dutifull Child be outragious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his loving Father for a ſlight correction, when as (for his groſſe offences) he deſerves an heavy puniſhment? Will the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mariner be offended at a boyſterous wind, which (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) to him is a favourable gale to bring him to his wiſhed Port? God (yea, our gracious God) dealeth with his Children, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> with his Brother <hi>Benjamin; Joſeph</hi> put his Cup into <hi>Benjamin</hi>'s ſacke, that he might returne againe to him: ſo God
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97183:16"/>cauſeth his <hi>Benjamins</hi> (his Children) to drinke of the cup of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, that (when they have offended by riding full ſpeed after their owne vaine imaginations) they may make a gentle retreat (through patience) into the communicative lines of Gods free acceptance. We are empty of goodneſſe; no marvell then, if God dealeth with us, as the Gardiner with the Buckets of his Well, who brings them downe, that he may fill them: God caſts us downe by affliction, that he may raiſe us up full of the grace of patience. In the time of proſperity, the regenerate do hold forth the white Roſe of innocency; but in the time of adverſity, the red Roſe of ſubmiſſive meekneſſe. Are we (therefore) in any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, diſtreſſe, or calamity, either in reſpect of health, wealth, friends, freedome, good-name, nay, life it ſelfe? Let us (I beſeech you) ſay with the holy Church (<hi>Mic.</hi> 7.9.) <hi>I will beare the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him.</hi> Nay, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affliction brings us home to God, let us come home unto, yea, into our ſelves, and <hi>poſſeſſe our foules with patience,</hi> which (as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſpeakes) is, <hi>animarum anima,</hi> the ſoule of ſoules; for, as we poſſeſſe our bodies by our ſoules, ſo we poſſeſſe our ſoules by patience: Yea (Beloved) as we all offend in many things, ſet us all be obedient in this one thing, <hi>viz: To runne with patience the race that is ſet before us, looking towards Jeſus, the Author and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of our faith:</hi> For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, is this the height of our terrene perfection, and the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our earthly glory, to have our coate of <hi>Or,</hi> and our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation <hi>Sable;</hi> to be graced with the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and to be diſgraced with the <hi>Tract</hi> of <hi>Malefactours;</hi> to be all endowed with integrity, and yet all to be brim-full of infirmity? Oh then! <hi>Qualis imitatio noſtra?</hi> How ſhould our imitation be qualified? <hi>Greg: Naz:</hi> in his panegyricall Oration in the behalfe of Saint <hi>Baſit,</hi> ſaith, that his Pariſhioners ſo dearly and truly affected, and ſo wonderfully admired him for his virtues, as every one's care and vigilancy was unanimouſly to imitate whatſoever was in him. And <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 5.) declares that the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> would imitate their Princes, even in their naturall defects and mutilati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Would God my fellow-ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> that cry up Chriſtianity ſo highly (indeed none can doe more) would imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the virtues, or rather, excellent graces of their unparallelled
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97183:16"/>gracious Soveraigne: Yet know, that <hi>Humanum eſt errare;</hi> and, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi> Let us not therefore draw the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and deformities of others in <hi>lively</hi> colours, and pourtray their comely feature in <hi>dead:</hi> Let not others evill actions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a copy for us to write after; but (as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth counſell us, ſaying) <hi>Si quid boni, à nobis eſt imitandum; ſi quid mali, à nobis eſt fugiendum:</hi> If we ſee any good in other men, let us imitate them in that; if any evill, let us ſhun and avoyd them in that. Agreeable hereunto is that counſell of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>Be ye Followers of me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as I am of Chriſt; i. e.</hi> So farre forth as I follow Chriſt, ſo farre forth doe ye follow me, and no further; for I have my frailties and imperfections; and the beſt of us, that are Miniſters, are but men, and ſubject to the like paſſions with you. If a man ſhould finde a piece of gold co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over with dirt, will he poſſeſſe himſelfe of the dirt, and throw away the gold? A Scholler that hath a copy ſet him, which is well penned, but ſomewhat defaced with certaine blots; in imitating the copy, will he imitate the blots? As (therefore) the <hi>Pilot</hi> lookes to the <hi>Northerne Starre</hi> to bring him to his wiſhed <hi>Part:</hi> ſo let our eies be ſet upon the good actions of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (for our imitation) to bring us to the <hi>Haven</hi> of eternall happineſſe: For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, Are all in this ſad predicamentall relation? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, &amp; Tremor?</hi> Where is our Feare, and Dread? It is proper to God (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) to doe what he will; to man, to doe what he can: But now the World is turned copſy-turvy; God doth what he can, and man what he will: Every man will be a law of liberty unto himſelfe; and that which ſhould be unto him for his wealth he makes an occaſion of falling; yea, of violent ruſhing into ſinne, as the Horſe into the battle.</p>
            <p>Moſt men will ſweare; nay, ſhall their oathes drop out of their mouthes, like <hi>Joab</hi>'s ſword out of his ſheath? Rather, they will ſend them forth like a flock of birds, hundreds together, becauſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſwore by the life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> They will wallow in the ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king puddle of drunkenneſſe, and ſenſuality, becauſe <hi>Noah</hi> was overtaken with his owne Wine. They will robbe, and plunder, and levell the eſtates of their brethren, becauſe the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> (though by an eſpeciall warrant from <hi>God,</hi> for their good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97183:17"/>robb'd the Ethnick <hi>Egyptians.</hi> They will account unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be but a veniall ſinne, becauſe <hi>David</hi> committed adultery. They ſay not, we <hi>doe,</hi> but, we <hi>will</hi> offend: like unto <hi>Ceſar</hi>'s <hi>jacta eſt alea,</hi> fall backe, fall edge, we <hi>will</hi> perſiſt in our ſinnes: Or, like <hi>Catiline,</hi> who when he had fired the City of <hi>Rome</hi> with his conſpiracies, had no more grace then to ſay, <hi>Incendium meum ruinâ extinguam,</hi> I will quench the fire I have kindled with a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ruine; I will adde worſe to evill, thirſt to drunkenneſſe, and leave the ſucceſſe of my wicked and ungracious actions to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt adventures. Is not this a witting, wilfull, and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offending? Surely this not a ſtumbling, and a falling into ſin; for, <hi>Praeventio dici non poteſt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Jerome) cùm quid prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditatò fit:</hi> That man cannot be ſaid to be prevented, who doth any thing upon ſerious premeditation. And ſhall we ſinne, that grace may abound? God forbid. If we goe into ſinne, as <hi>Siſera</hi> into <hi>Jacl</hi>'s Tent, it will ſmite us to the earth. If we allow our ſelves any one ſinne, as taking encouragement from the infirmities of the Saints, God will blot us out of the Booke of life. If we ſuffer our ſinnes to come one on the neck of another, like the Meſſengers of <hi>Job,</hi> our puniſhments muſt needs follow, like the plagues of <hi>Egypt.</hi> If we thinke to pleaſe God, in pleaſing our perverſe nature, the anger of the Lord will ſmoke in fury againſt us therefore. Let (therefore) the fallings of the Saints be our ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, their ſinnes our motives to amendment of life, and their tranſgreſſions make us more watchfull over our waies, more ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of our weakneſſe, and more forward to flee to God for his aſſiſtance in the way to Heaven. If this be done to the green tree, what to the dry? If to the beſt, what to the bad? If God ſuffers his deare Children to fall into ſinne, let us looke narrowly to our ſelves, and walke cautelouſly and circumſpectly in all our waies, and (as much as lyeth in us) ſhun all occaſions of evill; yea, let us worke out our ſalvation with feare and trembling; and pray to our gracious God, with the heart and words of <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>Keepe thy Servant from preſumptuous ſinnes, leſt they get the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over men ſo ſhall I be undefiled and innocent from the great of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:</hi> For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, are we all found guilty before <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Tribunall</hi> of juſtice? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi fiducia noſtra?</hi> where is our faith and confidence? Why
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97183:17"/>doe not we flie to his ſeat of mercy? when we doe approach <hi>that,</hi> with true faith and repentance, we ſhall aſſuredly obtaine the free pardon and forgiveneſſe of all our ſinnes. Our teares of contrition, by the mercies of <hi>God</hi> through the pretious blood and merits of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall waſh us throughly from our ſinnes. The blood of Chriſt will make our ſcarlet, crimſon ſinnes, as white as ſnow and wooll. Though a man (in perſecution) deny Chriſt, and renounce his Religion; yet he may be reſtored and repent, as <hi>Peter, Luke</hi> 22.32. Although a man be a great Idolater, Sorcerer, or given to Witchcraft, yet God may receive him into mercy, as he did <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> 2 Chron. 33. Some among the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were Fornicators, Adulterers, Wantons, and Buggerers, Thieves, Covetous, Drunkards, Raylers, and Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners; yet, were they <hi>waſhed, ſanctified, and juſtified in the name of the Lord Jeſus, and by the Spirit of our God,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 11. None are exempted from pardon, but ſuch as totally and finally deny Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.37. or, ſuch as are guilty of a univerſall, totall and finall Apoſtacy and Impenitency, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6. Or, (laſtly) ſuch as wilfully and malitiouſly renounce the known truth. Let us with comfort aſſure our ſelves, there is hope in ſtore for great and heinous Offenders; (contrary to the groſſe opinion of the <hi>Novatians</hi> and others, who teach that ſinnes committed after a maſs converſion are unpardonable) for, though we offend in many things, we remaine <hi>God's</hi> Children ſtill: for, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Jerome</hi> propoundeth a fit queſtion out of thoſe words of <hi>Salomon</hi> (<hi>Prov.</hi> 24.16.) <hi>A juſt man falleth ſeven times and riſeth up againe,</hi> and he anſwers it as comfortable, <hi>viz: Si juſtus, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo cadit? ſi cadit, quomodo juſtus? Nunquam amittit nomen juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiae, qui reſurgit per poenitentiam;</hi> If he be a righteous man, how comes it to paſſe that he falleth? If he falleth, how can he be a righteous man? He never loſeth (ſaith he) the name of a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, that riſeth againe by repentance. Who will ſay that that man's hands are dirty, who, (but even now) waſhed them cleane? Wherefore, let us not deſpaire of mercy and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſay with <hi>Cain, My ſinne is greater than can be pardoned:</hi> If we doe, we deſerve Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>'s objurgation, <hi>Mentiris Cain, mentiris in gutture,</hi> thou lieſt <hi>Cain,</hi> thou lieſt in thy throat,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97183:18"/>Gods mercies are more than thy ſinnes, and the Lords compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion greater than thy tranſgreſſion. It was a greater ſinne in <hi>Judas</hi> (ſaith he) to hang himſelfe, than to betray his Lord and Maſter. God hath but drops of juſtice; but flouds of mercy, one day for judgement, but a whole yeare for pardon. <hi>Chriſt Jeſus hath fully ſatisfied the juſtice of God, Coloſſ.</hi> 2.14. he hath cancelled the bond of our debts, and, <hi>waſhed us in his pretious blood, Revel.</hi> 1.5. He was puniſhed that we might be pardoned, he was condemned that we might be juſtified: The Lords ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing and over-flowing fountaine, is <hi>ſtill ſet open for ſinne and for uncleanneſſe, Zach.</hi> 13.1. Where the Spirit and the Spouſe ſay, <hi>Come,</hi> and let him that is a thirſt, come, and let whoſoever will, come, and take of the water of life freely, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Come unto me</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>all ye that are weary and heavy laden and I will eaſe you.</hi> Behold, he ſweetly invites us, <hi>[Come:]</hi> he plainly directs us <hi>[to me:]</hi> he ſtrongly incites us, <hi>[all ye that are weary and heavy laden:]</hi> and he freely promiſeth, <hi>[and I will eaſe you.] O quantum amoris!</hi> Oh what, and how much love! It is <hi>mandatum amoris,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) a commadement ſugred with love; <hi>Dulcis Domini, dulce mandatum,</hi> a ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, proceeding from a ſweet Lord and Maſter. Let us therefore flie to this rock of defence, and fountaine of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in our moſt bitter agonies; yea, when the ſorrowes of hell and death are comming upon us. It is ſaid of the Woman in the Goſpel, who was troubled with a bloody Iſſue, that ſhe came behind Chriſt and touched the hemme of his garment. Why (ſaith a Father) did ſhe not come before him, or, on one ſide of him; but behind him? Becauſe (ſaith he) ſhe would have Chriſt between God and her: So, let us get Chriſt between God and us, by a true and lively faith, and then we ſhall be ſure to find him unto us a mercifull Mediatour, Interceſſour, and gracious Redeemer. And let us ſay confidently and comfortably with Saint <hi>Auſelme, Etſi Domine, ego commiſi unde me damnare potes, tu tamen non amiſiſti unde me ſalvare potes:</hi> O bleſſed Lord, though I have committed thoſe tranſgreſſions, for which thou mayſt juſtly damne me: Yet I know thou haſt not loſt thoſe compaſſions by which thou mayſt ſave me. Thou haſt mercy for <hi>us all,</hi> who doe not ſinne through malitious wickedneſſe. And
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97183:18"/>thy mercies are not a few, but <hi>many,</hi> becauſe, <hi>In many things we offend all. Have mercy</hi> (therefore) <hi>upon us (O Lord) after thy great goodneſſe, according to the multitude of thy mercies, doe away our offences, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, (to ſumme up all in few words, leſt I my ſelfe ſhould offend too, in preſſing too much upon your patience) are we thus abaſed, through our owne inherent corruption, and daily tranſgreſſing, and ſhall not we therefore now be throughly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſhed? <hi>Qualis est regulatio noſtra?</hi> What manner of Chriſtian ſubmiſſion doe we carry towards the ſet rule of God, and that lawfull Authority, ſet up and confirmed by him? What is our carriage and deportment towards our Maker, and towards Man; towards our heavenly Father, and our earthly Brethren? May not I aske, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi eſt humilitas, &amp; charitas noſtra?</hi> Where is our Humility, and Charity? Firſt, where is our Humility? Doe we yeild unto our Inferiours? Doe we give place to our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals? or rather, Doe we not inſult over our Betters; our Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, both in the phraſe of the World, and in the language of <hi>Ganaan;</hi> our Betters, in riches and honours, and in grace and goodneſſe? Is not that in our daily practiſe (touching the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy and Miniſtry) for which <hi>Korah</hi> and his company pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, though they did but utter, and that but once too, againſt <hi>Moſe:</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Ye take too much upon you? Num.</hi> 16.3. Are not many of us like unto <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caeſar;</hi> for, <hi>Pompey</hi> could abide no Equall, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> could ſuffer no Superiour? Alas! How vainly are we puft up with a ſtrong conceit of our owne <hi>[crooked]</hi> uprightneſſe, and <hi>[ſinfull]</hi> holineſſe! How doe we vaunt and boaſt of the good we doe, of the goods we have and of the victories we obtaine! Yet, if we would trie our ſelves by the touch-ſtone of Gods holy word, we ſhould find our ſelves unprofitable Servants, and be enforced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dionyſius</hi> thought his God had bleſt him for robbing <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> his Tent; becauſe he had a favourable and proſperous gale: So, many doe wax proud of their owne <hi>[nocent]</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency; becauſe they are ſtill proſperous and ſucceſsfull in all their wicked and unjuſt deſignes: As if the ſucceſſe ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly prove the juſtneſſe of the cauſe, and the juſtice of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97183:19"/>act. Surely, if ſo, the Turke may proudly maintaine his Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane Religion to be the true, and his bloody and abominable converſation to be unblamable: For, (through the Chriſtians diviſions) with his bow and ſheild he hath conquered the greateſt part of Chriſtendome. The Laodiceans were proud of their condition; They ſaid, <hi>they were rich, and increaſed in goods, and had need of nothing, Revel.</hi> 3.17. yet, were they <hi>wretched, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and poore, and blind, and naked.</hi> The proud <hi>Phariſee</hi> would caſt up the number of his good deeds, with, <hi>I thanke thee that I am not as other men, or as this Publican.</hi> But, (for all that) he was ſo faulty, and the more for that; that he was condemned, and the faulty <hi>Publican</hi> through his humility was juſtified. It is (doubtleſſe) farre better to be humbly ſinfull, then proudly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for, to be poore in ſpirit, is to be rich in ſoule. I beſeech you therefore (my deare Brethren) <hi>Be not many Maſters, knowing, that we ſhall receive the greater condemnation, Jam.</hi> 3.1. for, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is as lawfull to be <hi>Maſters,</hi> as to be <hi>Fathers;</hi> but, we muſt not be ambitious, vain-glorious, intruding, uſurping <hi>Maſters,</hi> ſuch as doe go before they are ſent; ſuch as, without a lawfull call, rule, or warrant, doe take upon them (like proud temerarious <hi>Phaeton</hi>) to guide the <hi>Chariot</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> and <hi>Church.</hi> Saint <hi>Auſtine,</hi> the <hi>Ordinary Gloſſe, Bede, Luther, &amp;c.</hi> doe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by theſe <hi>Maſters,</hi> ſuch as doe take upon them to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when as they themſelves are ſo ignorant, as that they need to be taught. Saint <hi>James</hi> wrote this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to his Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were converted and diſperſed, who though they were in ſome meaſure Proficients in <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Schoole; yet, would be dehort them from too much forwardneſſe in undertaking the inſtructing of others: And that becauſe this their ambition would bring upon them the greater condemnation; and he doth illuſtrate, how, for, ſaith he, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All of us deſerve condemnation, or judgement, for our many offences: but, they who ſinne in this high nature, doe deſerve and ſhall aſſuredly receive the greater judgement, or condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Let not then the <hi>Shrub</hi> think it ſelf as good as the <hi>Cedar:</hi> Let not the feet ſtand in the place of the head: Let every one be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97183:19"/>content with that calling or condition of life which God hath beſtowed on him: Let him not be a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in another man's <hi>Dioceſſe;</hi> but let every man move in his owne Orbe. If thou beeſt a <hi>Mechanick,</hi> or <hi>Tradeſ-man,</hi> doe not take upon thee to be a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine:</hi> If thou findeſt thy ſelfe furniſhed with ſpirituall gifts, uſe them to the edification of thy family: Inſult not, intrude not, uſurpe not over, nor into the Miniſtery: <hi>Be not many Maſters;</hi> nay, <hi>be not any Maſters,</hi> in this ſenſe: But let us be clothed with humility, and in lowlineſſe of minde, thinke another mans gifts better than our own: Let us not be high-minded, but feare; and walke humbly with our God, and he will exalt us; he will give us his grace here, and glory hereafter. But if we will be ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and goe beyond the bounds and limits that God hath ſet us, we ſhall have <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s doome, and receive the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Charitas noſtra?</hi> Where is our <hi>Charity?</hi> What is become of thoſe noble pair of Lovers <hi>David</hi> &amp; <hi>Jonathan,</hi> who had but one heart? <hi>Pilades</hi> and <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> who had but one life (the one being dead, the other died alſo?) <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Naomi,</hi> who could not be parted? <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Anima una erat incluſa in duobus corporibus,</hi> One ſoule was included in two bodies? They are dead, and (in truth) ſo is our love. In the <hi>Primitive times</hi> there was ſo much love amongſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that it was, <hi>ad ſtuporem Gentilium,</hi> to the aſtoniſhment of the <hi>Heathen;</hi> inſomuch that they would point with the finger, with an <hi>Ecce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t invicem ſe diligunt!</hi> See, fee, oh how entirely do the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians love one another! But, in theſe daies there is ſo little love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that it is, <hi>ad pudorem Chriſtianorum,</hi> to the ſhame of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> for (as learned <hi>Zanchy</hi> ſpeakes) <hi>Ecce ut invicem ſe oderunt;</hi> Behold, how they hate one another, revile, perſecute, and murther one another.</p>
            <p>May not I truly complaine (with Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) and ſay;
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O the cruelty! O the ſavageneſſe! O the inhumanity of us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians!</hi> We ſhew our ſelves to be borne in <hi>Thebes,</hi> and not in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> and to be of the true <hi>Cadmean</hi> brood, becauſe we take ſo much delight in killing and deſtroying one another. That Poet
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97183:20"/>both wittily and truly divided the World into foure ages, <hi>viz:</hi> the golden, the ſilver, the leaden, and the iron age: And ſurely, if ever any people lived in this laſt age, we of <hi>England</hi> (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) doe at this time; for, if we looke for mercy, behold cruelty; if for juſtice, behold oppreſſion; if for righteouſneſſe, behold a cry; if for love and charity, behold envy, hatred, and malice, and all uncharitableneſſe; from which, yea, from all which (it ſhall be my daily <hi>Letanie</hi> to ſay) <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shall not we that are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> conſider one another, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke unto Love? Shall not we lay to heart our owne erring con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that we may the more commiſerate thoſe that doe ſinne againſt us? <hi>Be not many Maſters</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>James</hi>) i.e. (as <hi>Piſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> and <hi>Pareus, &amp;c.</hi>) doe not over-ſtrictly marke, and then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely cenſure, and raſhly condemne the words and actions of your brethren, and afterwards them for thoſe; backbite not, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract not, defame not, ſlander not, nor inſult over them for their tranſgreſſions; for, <hi>In many things we offend all. Let him that ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall;</hi> and let him remember, That <hi>there ſhall be judgement mercileſſe, to him that will ſhew no mercy:</hi> And, <hi>Nihil ad miſericordiam ſic inclinat</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin) quantum proprii periculi conſideratio:</hi> Nothing doth make a man ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to mercy and compaſſion, as the conſideration of the danger himſelfe is in continually, and what he hath already juſtly deſerved at Gods hand. The ſight of the eye (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) hath no colour, that ſo it may diſcerne all colours: So if we were not guilty of ſinne our ſelves, it might be more tollerable for us to pry into the lives and converſations of others, and to ſhew them no pity, who will make themſelves ſo filthy: But far be it from us to throw ſtones at others, when as we deſerve to be ſtoned our ſelves: Let us not be ſo naſty, as to lay our filthy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane hands on the freckled faces of our brethren. <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 6.1. <hi>if a man be fallen by occaſion, into any fault, ye which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one with the ſpirit of meekneſſe,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doe unto him, as a <hi>Chyrurgion</hi> unto his Patient, who hath a legge or an arme diſlocated, uſe him tenderly and gently) <hi>conſidering thy ſelfe, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi> Such a conſtruction Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> made of the fall of his Brother; for he wept bitterly, uſing theſe words, <hi>Ille hodie, &amp; ego cras;</hi> he hath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97183:20"/>fallen this day, and I not unlikely to fall to morrow: So when we ſee others fall into ſin, let us exhort and admoniſh, reprove gently, direct wiſely, and comfort without flattery: However, let us mourne, and pray for them. <hi>Whoſoever walketh according to theſe rules, peace ſhall be upon him, and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God:</hi> For, <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Glory be to God on high, and on earth peace, good will towards men.</hi> Amen, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. lin. 24. for <hi>ſight,</hi> reade <hi>ſite.</hi> Pag. 6. lin. 6. for <hi>Sentius,</hi> r. <hi>Sextius.</hi> Pag. 6. lin. 18. for <hi>c.</hi> 7. r. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If thou findeſt any more litterall faults, I pray thee paſſe by, or amend them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
